Guide to the Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. Papers 1808-1976 MS 438
New-York Historical Society
- Series III. New York Supreme Court, 1938-1965; 3.8 Linear feet in five record cartons and in oversize folders
  - Reference Letters (3 folders), 1946-1963 (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Oversize Supreme Court Campaign Poster, Undated (Box Oversize Large)
    Endorses Edgar J. Nathan, Jr., Macdonald Dewitt, and Michael R. Matteo for Supreme Court.
  - Oversize Supreme Court Campaign Poster, Undated (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Print Matter, 1954-1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Contains book of court cases that Nathan presided over (corresponds to "Volume 4" of Supreme Court scrapbooks), address book of New York Supreme Court justices in 1958, a bound interview transcript of Nathan explaining his genealogy back to Abraham de Lucena, and Nathan's certificate of service as a retired Supreme Court justice.
  - Photographs, 1946-1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Includes photographs of Nathan being sworn in as New York Supreme Court Justice by New York Secretary of State Thomas J. Curran, photographs of Nathan with Governor Thomas E. Dewey, and photographs of New York Supreme Court events.
  - Typescripts of Campaign Clippings (Folder 1 of 3), 1939 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Campaign Clippings (2 folders of 3), 1939 (Box 19, Folder 19-20)
  - Clippings (3 folders), 1946-1965 (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
  - Yiddish Newspaper Clippings, 1939 (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Clippings Scrapbook of Nathan Cases (4 volumes of 7), 1938-1960 (Box 15, Volume 1-4)
    Volume 1 contains some unrelated material, including some clippings about the Jewish Theological Seminary and the Constitutional Convention of 1938.
  - Clippings Scrapbook of Nathan Cases (3 volumes of 7), 1956-1965 (Box 16, Volume 1-3)
- Series IV. Jewish Leadership, 1896-1967; 1 Linear feet in one record carton
  The series is arranged by subject matter, beginning with papers related to Shearith Israel and advancing to Jewish correspondence and print matter. General correspondence is followed by papers related to the 300th anniversary (tercentenary) of the arrival of Jews to America and founding of the Shearith Israel Congregation and the 50th anniversary (semi-centennial) of the founding of the Jewish Theological Seminary. The series concludes with photographs.
  The series is comprised of correspondence, memorabilia, clippings, speeches, and print matter related to Edgar J. Nathan's Jewish life and leadership, including his activity in various Jewish organizations such as Shearith Israel, where he was president, and the Jewish Theological Seminary, where he was on the Board of Directors. Many of the materials in the series are related to specific events which Nathan helped plan, including tercentenary celebrations (both for Shearith Israel and for a larger Jewish audience) and the semi-centennial celebration of JTS. The tercentenary files also include a signed note from Dwight D. Eisenhower. Other information on Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s Jewish life and leadership can be found throughout the collection, but especially in the speeches segment of Series II. Manhattan Borough Presidency (Box 2, Folders 5-12) and in Series VI and VII (Print Matter and Memorabilia).
  - Misc. Shearith Israel Papers, 1896-1967 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Contains clippings and programs from the Mill Street Synagogue's 200th anniversary celebrations, programs from 1896 dedication of the synagogue, speeches and reports from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s presidency, and bulletins from 1925-1964.
  - Misc. Jewish Correspondence and Print Matter (1 folder of 4), 1941-1961 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Contains print matter from various Jewish organizations, including the Jewish Social Service Association.
  - Misc. Jewish Correspondence and Print Matter (3 folders of 4), 1815-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    Contains print matter from various Jewish organizations, including the Jewish Social Service Association. Folder 3 contains newspaper clippings about various Jewish events and topics, including articles/essays about and by Solomon Schechter, as well as a photocopy of an 1815 article on Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s ancestors on the Solis side opening a dry goods store.
  - Tercentenary Speeches, 1948-1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Mainly tercentenary speeches and speech drafts, but also includes unrelated 1948 Jewish speech.
  - Tercentenary Papers (Folder 1 of 7), 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Contains invitation to dinner honoring Jacob Javits and a copy of a speech by then-president Dwight D. Eisenhower as well as tercentenary material. Also includes photographs from the event.
  - Tercentenary Papers (Folder 2 of 7), 1954 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Letter to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. from President Dwight D. Eisenhower.
  - Tercentenary Papers (3 folders of 7), 1948-1956 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
    Various correspondence and print matter from tercentenary, except a few seemingly random letters from 1948 in Folder 9.
  - Tercentenary Papers (2 folders of 7), 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    Scrapbooks.
  - Jewish Theological Seminary Papers (6 folders), 1918-1961 (Box 4, Folder 12-17)
    Mainly contains correspondence and print matter related to 1937 JTS semi-centennial celebration, in addition to print matter from the 1910s with "E.N.S." inscribed on the covers of some booklets.
  - Photographs, 1951-1964 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Series V. General Correspondence, 1900-1976; 4.4 Linear feet in five record cartons and in oversize folders
  The series is arranged into two subseries:
  Subseries V.A Subject Files
  Subseries V.B Chronological Files
  The series contains mostly personal correspondence, including bills, receipts, condolences, and congratulations, the bulk of which is from the 1930s and 1940s. The series also includes some correspondence from or about various politicians and Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s political life.
  - Subseries V.A Subject Files, 1914-1976; 1.45 Linear feet in three record cartons
    The subseries is arranged in original subject folders and grouped together by topic.
    The subseries begins with condolences for Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s father's death, his mother's death, his cousin, Justice Benjamin N. Cardozo's death, his aunt's death, and finally his own death, coupled with acknowledgments for gifts made in Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s name, and obituaries/memorial papers for Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. The series then advances to congratulations, birthday wishes (including some from prominent politicians), correspondence in regards to jobs Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. held outside of politics, including with the War Trade Board and the law firm Cardozo & Nathan, and a failed attempt to secure a position as Assistant Attorney General. The subseries also contains a folder of correspondence regarding Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s sons, which includes correspondence both with and about them.
    - Condolences for Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.'s Death (3 folders), 1929-1931 (Box 4, Folder 19-21)
    - Condolences for Sara Solis Nathan (Mother)'s Death (3 folders), 1937 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Condolences for Justice Cardozo's Death, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Includes telegram from Charles C. Burlingham on his friendship with Cardozo.
    - Condolences for Esther Solis (Aunt)'s Death, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Contains one letter addressed to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s other aunt, Elvira.
    - Condolences for Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s Death (8 folders), 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6-13)
      Letters from friends and family (including many local New York politicians) addressed primarily to Edgar J. Nathan, III and Mabel Nathan (Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s widow).
    - Acknowledgements re: Gifts Made in Edgar J. Nathan's Name, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Obituaries and Memorial Papers for Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. (1 folder of 2), 1965 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Includes some correspondence re: donations made in Edgar J. Nathan's name. Also includes program for memorial services. More of this material can be found in Series VII. Memorabilia.
    - Obituaries and Memorial Papers for Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. (Folder 2 of 2), 1965 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Newspaper clippings of obituaries.
    - Congratulations on Return to Law Practice (3 folders), 1946 (Box 5, Folder 16-18)
      Partnership with Gale, Bernays, Falk, etc.
    - Acknowledgements of Congratulations (2 folders), 1946 (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
    - 70th Birthday Wishes (4 folders), 1914-1962 (bulk 1961) (Box 5, Folder 21-24)
      In addition to birthday wishes, contains invitations to parties and ceremonies honoring Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. for his birthday, as well as some cards wishing Nathan a speedy recovery after surgery. Folder 22 contains birthday letters from former President Dwight D. Eisenhower, New York Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller, and former Governor Thomas E Dewey. Folder 24 contains pictures of birthday party, a random piece of correspondence from 1943, a photograph from 1914 of Nathan and family on the Mt. Washington Railway, and other mementos from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s life.
    - Post-Death Correspondence Re: Possible Book, 1901-1976 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      Contains correspondence between Edgar J. Nathan, III and Phyllis Stahl-Berkowitz, who was interested in writing an historical account of early Jewish American families. Also contains clippings and memorial materials about Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. that Edgar J. Nathan, III likely gave to Stahl-Berkowitz as research material.
    - Personal—Re: Washington (2 folders), 1918-1921 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
      Contains correspondence about Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s failed attempt at an Assistant Attorney General position and work at the War Trade Board in WWI.
    - War Trade Board Correspondence (2 folders), 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
      Among the documents is Nathan, Jr's will as of 1918.
    - Alumni Awards Correspondence (Folder 1 of 2), 1942-1958 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Correspondence related to awards and honorary degrees given to Nathan by Collegiate School, Columbia University, and Williams College.
    - Alumni Awards Correspondence (Folder 2 of 2), 1955 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Edgar, 3rd and Frederic, 1931-1954 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      Correspondence about and with Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s sons. Also includes two letters from Justice Benjamin Cardozo to one of the sons, Edgar J. Nathan, 3rd.
    - Cardozo & Nathan Correspondence (2 folders), 1923-1941 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
      Contains documents from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s law practice era, including financial statements and partnership agreements. Also contains correspondence with Justice Benjamin Cardozo. Similar material can be found in chronological folders.
  - Subseries V.B Chronological Files, 1900-1964; 2.95 Linear feet in three record cartons and in oversize folders
    The subseries is arranged in original chronological folder order, and within each folder remains in original rough alphabetical order, except for the "Early Life Correspondence," which was gathered from miscellaneous folders, and the 1951-1964 folders, which were found grouped together, but were not alphabetized.
    The subseries begins with two letterpress copybooks and three binders of carbon copies, which contain Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s outgoing correspondence from 1920-1931, and a folder of miscellaneous correspondence from 1900-1925, which contains both incoming and outgoing personal correspondence from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s childhood and young adulthood. The remaining folders in the subseries primarily contain personal correspondence from family members and friends including Henry S. Hendricks, Benjamin N. Cardozo, Charles C. Burlingham, and Charles Sears, as well as extensive documents concerning routine bills, charitable donations, insurance (including lists of personal and other property owned), banking, and investments. The investments often relate to real estate and there are financial statements for the various realty companies involved (e.g., Grand Atlantic Corporation, Greenington Realty, Sunnington Realty). The subseries also contains some political materials, including brief notes from Thomas Dewey, Fiorello LaGuardia, and Herbert Lehman, invitations to Lehman and Nelson Rockefeller's inaugurations, anti-Franklin Delano Roosevelt print matter and an oversize cartoon stamp sheet, and various other documents related to Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s political and Jewish life.
    - Letterpress Copybook, 1920-1922 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Letterpress Copybook, 1922-1926 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Carbon Copies, 1926-1928 (Box 9, Volume 1)
    - Carbon Copies, 1928-1930 (Box 9, Volume 2)
    - Carbon Copies, 1930-1931 (Box 9, Volume 3)
    - Early Life Correspondence, 1900-1925 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Includes a letter sent to Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.
    - 1929-1931 Correspondence and Bills (8 folders), 1926-1931 (Box 6, Folder 10-17)
    - 1931-1934 Correspondence and Bills (8 folders) (Box 6, Folder 18-25)
    - 1935-1936 Correspondence and Bills (3 folders of 9), 1933-1936 (Box 6, Folder 26-28)
      Contains a brief note from Governor Thomas Dewey in Folder 28.
    - 1935-1936 Correspondence and Bills (5 folders of 9), 1931-1936 (Box 7, Folder 1-5)
    - 1935-1936 Correspondence and Bills (Folder 9 of 9) (Box Oversize Small, Folder 2)
      Oversize perforated sheet of Republican Council anti-FDR cartoon poster-stamps. Informational sheet that came with stamps can be found in Box 7, Folder 5.
    - 1937 Correspondence and Bills (6 folders), 1911-1937 (Box 7, Folder 6-11)
      Contains correspondence related to Thomas Dewey's first campaign for governor and correspondence with Justice Benjamin N. Cardozo. Also contains in the third folder an unlabeled, undated photograph (perhaps of Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. and his wife, Sara Solis Nathan, or another pair of relatives). Folder 1 holds an illustrated prospectus for Sweet's Steel Company of Williamsport, Pennsylvania (1937).
    - 1938 Correspondence and Bills (8 folders), 1926-1938 (Box 7, Folder 12-19)
      Contains correspondence and bills related to Justice Benjamin N. Cardozo's illness and death, the 1938 Constitutional Convention, Thomas E. Dewey's campaign for District Attorney (including a letter of thanks from Dewey in folder 14), as well as correspondence related to Nathan's law practice. Includes an (impersonal) letter from LaGuardia in folder 17.
    - 1939 Correspondence and Bills (8 folders), 1936-1939 (Box 7, Folder 20-27)
      Contains various political materials, including materials from Edgar J. Nathan, Jr.'s first Supreme Court campaign, a letter from Mayor Fiorello LaGuardia (in folder 24), and an invitation to Governor Herbert H. Lehman's inauguration.
    - 1940 Correspondence and Bills (7 folders), 1937-1941 (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
      Contains anti-FDR/pro-Willkie campaign materials, including booklets and papers condemning the concept of a president running for a third term (mainly in folder 6). Folder 3 and others contains documents concerning the Greater New York Interfaith Committee's effort to get legislation passed allowing release time in public schools for religious education. Folder 7 contains affidavits of support for two people to come to the U.S. from Europe.
    - 1944-1947 Correspondence and Bills (7 folders), 1942-1947 (Box 8, Folder 8-14)
      Mostly contains receipts and bills. Limited World War II-related correspondence.
    - 1947-1950 Correspondence and Bills (3 folders), 1942-1950 (Box 8, Folder 15-17)
      Contains political materials throughout, including brief correspondence with Governors Dewey and Lehman. Also contains Supreme Court correspondence and Jewish leadership correspondence. Folder 17 contains some Manhattan Borough Presidency correspondence from 1942.
    - 1951-1959 Correspondence and Bills, 1945-1959 (Box 8, Folder 18)
      Includes materials on Nelson Rockefeller's gubernatorial campaign, including an invitation to Rockefeller's inauguration.
    - 1960-1964 Correspondence and Bills (2 folders) (Box 8, Folder 19-20)
      Folder 20 contains undated, handwritten list of names and addresses of "Nathan friends."
- Series VI. Print Matter, 1881-1959; 2.3 Linear feet in five record cartons
  The series is organized into two subseries:
  Subseries V.A File Cabinet
  Subseries V.B Loose Print Matter
  The series primarily consists of essays, speeches, and booklets on Judaism, as well as a number of publications on contemporary political topics from a variety of time periods, including women's suffrage, prohibition, World War I, World War II, Theodore Roosevelt, and Zionism. Additionally, the series contains print matter related to Shearith Israel and Columbia University, and memorial booklets for various Jewish people.
  - Subseries VI.A File Cabinet, 1884-1926; .7 Linear feet in two record cartons
    The materials in the subseries were originally in a small file cabinet, and the folder labels in the subseries correspond to those originally found on the file cabinet drawers. Within each folder, the materials are arranged chronologically.
    The subseries contains print matter from 1884-1926, when Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. was still a young man. Though possible that the materials within the file cabinet were originally his, the date range and the repeated inscription of his father's name on the booklets suggests that perhaps the file cabinet originally belonged to Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. The materials within the series are Jewish and political in nature, mainly about Zionism, anti-Semitism, Russian pogroms, Presidents Woodrow Wilson and Theodore Roosevelt's foreign policies, and Shearith Israel.
    - Unlabeled, 1901-1914 (Box -, Folder -)
      - Invitation to Memorial Services for Pogrom Victims, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Program for Shearith Israel's 250th Anniversary Celebration, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Notes Relating to the Celebration of the 250th Anniversary of the Settlement of Jews in the United States, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Published by the Executive Committee.
      - Program for General Celebration of 250th Anniversary of Jewish Settlement in the United States, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Contains enclosed 1909 clipping naming Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. to review bar applications.
      - Program for 150th Anniversary of Columbia University's Founding, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Rosh Hashanah Sermon, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Preached by Rabbi H. Pereira Mendes, minister of Shearith Israel.
      - Shavuot Sermon, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Preached and inscribed ("with greetings") by Rabbi H. Pereira Mendes, minister of Shearith Israel.
      - Year Book of the Spanish and Portuguese Congregation Shearith Israel, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Jews in America, 1901 (Box 10, Folder 1)
        Reprint from the Jewish Encyclopedia.
    - Speeches—Jewish, 1884-1921 (Box -, Folder -)
      - Address Delivered at the Celebration of the Centennial Birthday of Sir Moses Montefiore, Bart., 1884 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Delivered by D. Solis Cohen, at Portland's New Market Theatre.
      - Abuse By Russia of the American Passport, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Speech to House of Representatives by Hon. Francis Burton Harrison.
      - Jewish Criminality in New York, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Reprint of The Independent article written by Francis J. Oppenheimer in response to anti-Semitic comments made by NYC Police Commissioner Theodore Bingham.
      - Russia and the American Passport, 1911 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Address given by attorney Louis Marshall to Union of American Hebrew Congregations with included resolution of council.
      - The Jewish Theological Seminary: Past and Future, 1918 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Address delivered by Solomon Solis Cohen, at JTS's 25th annual commencement.
      - Memorials Submitted to President Wilson Concerning the Status of the Jews..., 1919 (Box 10, Folder 2)
        Appeal by Representatives of the American Jewish Congress, inscribed by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.
      - Little Studies in Judaism I: Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Russian Persecution and American Jews in Russia, 1902 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Speech given to House of Representatives by Hon. Henry Goldfogle.
      - Russia's Abuse of American Passports, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Speech to House of Representatives by Hon. Henry M. Goldfogle.
      - Francis Burton Harrison Campaign Pamphlet, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Markets Harrison for Lieutenant-Governor as "a friend of the Jewish people."
      - A Reply to Justice Brewer's Lectures, 1908 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        A refutation of Justice David J. Brewer's postulate that the U.S. is a Christian nation, by Isaac Hassler.
      - Palestine and the Diaspora, 1913 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Written by D. de Sola Pool, a prominent Shearith Israel rabbi.
      - The "Protocols" Bolshevism and the Jews, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        An address for a Jewish audience by American Jewish Organizations.
      - The Tyranny of Intolerance, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Booklet written by C.A. Windle, in anser to Henry Ford's Case Against the Jews.
      - Shearith Israel Constitution and By-Laws, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Clippings, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 3)
        Poem about Russian anti-Semitism by Edwin Markham from The Jewish Comment and article from The New York Evening Journal about William Waldorf Astor's anti-Semitism.
    - Reports—General, 1903-1904 (Box -, Folder -)
      - Clippings, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Speech by Hon. George F. Hoar, 1902 (Box 10, Folder 4)
        Speech to U.S. Senate in support of Filipino independence in aftermath of Philippine-American War.
      - The Republican Party, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        Book with two pro-Republican speeches, one by John Hay and one by Elihu Root.
      - Mr. Roosevelt and the Presidency, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        Claims to be written by "A. Spectator," actually by Frederick W. Whitridge under a pseudonym.
      - Roosevelt or Parker, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 5)
        By Frederick W. Whitridge.
      - John Hay on Theodore Roosevelt, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Extract of pro-Republican address by John Hay.
      - An Open Letter to the Parker Constitution Club, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Written by Nathan Bijur in defense of President Theodore Roosevelt.
      - The Panama Canal, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Pro-Roosevelt speech delivered by Hon. Chauncey H. Depew to the U.S. Senate. Inscribed (likely by Edgar J. Nathan, Jr. due to the handwriting).
      - The New York Law Institute: Report of the Librarian, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Inscribed by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr. ("from M.H.C.").
      - Minutes from Hearing Before the Committee on Woman Suffrage, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - The Trusts, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 6)
        Speech to House of Representatives by Hon. William Harris Douglas.
      - The United Typothetae of America (Typographical Union) Circular, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Municipal Art Society of NY: Report of the Committee on Civic Centers, 1904 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Speeches—General, 1895-1926 (Box -, Folder -)
      - Annual Reports of The American Jewish Committee, 1922, 1926 (Box 10, Folder 7)
        Two reports (the fifteenth and nineteenth annual).
      - Addresses Delivered at Harvard Semitic Museum Opening, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Solomon Schechter's Jewish Theological Seminary Inaugural Address, 1903 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Views on the Synod, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        Compiled by Committee of the Central Conference of American Rabbis. Inscribed with Edgar J. Nathan, Sr.'s initials and contains enclosed 1905 clipping.
      - Ownership, by Edgar J. Nathan, Sr., 1915 (Box 10, Folder 8)
        Address delivered at 106th meeting of The Insurance Society of New York.
      - "The Position of Judaism", 1895 (Box 10, Folder 9)